<matrix>
    <stage position="1">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p><strong>Acquisitions &ndash; Land Banking (I.1.)</strong></p> <p><strong>Long term trends to increase value of the subject property:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Population growth usually caused by increased&nbsp;employment in the region</li> <li>Transportation improvements usually&nbsp;related to government sponsored project</li> <ul> <li>Interstate Highway or major local highway extensions or new exit</li> <li>&nbsp;Transit extensions and stations</li> </ul> </ul> <p>Bus (rubber tire)</p> <p>Street car lines</p> <p>Light rail</p> <p>Heavy rail</p> <p>Airport Expansions or new carriers</p> <p>Port facility expansions</p> <p>Intermodal developments</p> <ul> <li>Technology changes : such as</li> <ul> <li>driverless vehicles,</li> <li>renewable energy generation and storage,</li> <li>food production and processing,</li> <li>water treatment and recycling</li> <li>Solid waste processing</li> </ul> </ul> <p><strong>Capital partners be patient until the market changes occur.</strong></p> <ul> <li>Business&nbsp;cycles are 5-7 years in duration, usually.</li> <li>Government approvals and funding are indeterminist time wise.</li> <li>Federal,&nbsp;state and local government polices toward growth or land uses change constantly.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Analyze additional parcels for acquisitions (assemblage).</strong></p> <ul> <li>Adjacent land parcels&nbsp;may become available.</li> <li>Determine the value of the combined parcels (plottage value) relative to the cost the combined cos.t</li> </ul> <p><strong>Implement interim land use plan to minimize the carrying cost over time, if possible.</strong></p> <ul> <li>Interim&nbsp;land uses should lower the net holding costs of the property.</li> <li>Interim land uses should not lower the value of the property or upset the neighbors.</li> <li>Interim land uses should be relatively short term in nature.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Identify the critical conditions for the vision to occur:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Sustained regional&nbsp;economic growth</li> <li>Changed land use regulations</li> <li>Construction of transportation improvement</li> <li>Infrastructure capacity</li> </ul> <p><strong>Identify the major events or conditions that will make the vision obvious to the general market.</strong></p> <p><strong>Determine the vision for the property over the next 5 &ndash; 10 years:</strong></p> <ul> <li>A concept master plan&nbsp;will help the investors and the general public image what the property could be some day.</li> <li>Artists&rsquo; renderings are a great tool to demonstrate the vision.</li> <li>New employers&nbsp;in&nbsp;the region.</li> <li>New ad different elected political leaders.</li> <li>Changing tax policies.</li> <li>International trade opportunities.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Determine how the property be acquired and held for the expected holding period or longer if necessary.</strong></p> <ul> <li>Seller financing; The seller lends the buyer the money to property. This also referred to as a purchase money mortgage.</li> <li>Option agreements:&nbsp;buyer&nbsp;acquires the right to purchase the property at a specified sometime some time in the future. Extension provisions can very important</li> </ul> <p>Sales contract with conditions, pre-conditions to close: A sales contract can be used to control the property until&nbsp;certain condition are met prior to closing. Sales contract usually have non-refundable good faith deposits, and there are usually extension provisions in the contract.</p> <p>Lease with option to buy: land leases allow the lessee (prospective buyer) to control the property (subject to the lease provisions), and the lease has provisions allowing the lessor to purchase the property at certain times during the lease term. The price of the property should be specified, but often it is not so the purchase price is at the market value or at a price mutually agreed upon between the lessor and the lessee</p> <ul> <li>Land contracts: The land contract provides for the title to pass from the seller to the buyer after certain specific terms and conditions are met.&nbsp;</li> <li>Interim land uses: These can provide rental income to the land banker which help to defray the holding costs. These uses can be as simple as seasonal hunting lease or as complex as a long term commercial lease with termination provisions.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Establish minimum return requirements and expectations:&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;the land&nbsp;banker should clarify the return expectations for her investors and partners. For example the property will double in value in:</p> <ul> <li>Five&nbsp;years if the annual appreciation rate is&nbsp;15%</li> <li>Ten&nbsp;years if the annual appreciation rate is 7%</li> <li>Fifteen&nbsp;years if the annual appreciation rate is 5%</li> </ul> <p>Clearly, the faster the general trends occur, the sooner that property can be sold to the land packager, and the higher the return is to the land banker.</p> <p>Examples of this is at the following links:</p> <p><a href="http://www.dankohlhepp.com/">http://www.dankohlhepp.com</a></p> <p><a href="https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/bssv2_-_sustainability.pdf">https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/bssv2_-_sustainability.pdf</a></p> <p>Click on the link below to take you to the next Stage:</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162134/Acquisition%20Land%20Packaging%20Stage">Acquisition Land Packaging Stage</a></p> ]]></task>
        <task position="2">
            <![CDATA[<p>Financing &ndash; Land Banking (II.1.)</p> <p>Unreliable and inadequate annual income do not support debt payments.</p> <ul> <li>Regular debt payments require regular rental income of regular equity contributions.</li> <li>With our predictable income form interim land uses, debt should be avoided.</li> <li>Very low loan-to-value ratio (0 is best).</li> </ul> <p>Equity partners must understand and accept the risks of land banking.</p> <ul> <li>Land Banking is a waiting game and equity investor must be willing to wait for eventual returns from the sale of the property.</li> <li>Equity investors must be prepared to make additional equity contributions to meet annual cash shortfall because of required debt payments, insurance, or taxes.</li> </ul> <p>Cumulative preferred returns can sink the deal.</p> <ul> <li>Land bankers requiring additional equity may be tempted to offer new equity investors a cumulative, preferred return.</li> <li>The cumulative , proffered return is a claim on the eventual proceed s from the sale of the property.&nbsp;</li> <li>However, because of the compound effect of this return scheme, the new equity investors&rsquo; claim may</li> </ul> <p> exceed the net proceed from sale.</p> <p>Seller financing can be critical variable&nbsp;&bull;Seller financing.</p> <ul> <li>The&nbsp;buyer developer should look to the seller as a source funds to acquire the property.</li> <li>The selling&nbsp;developer should consider financing some of the sales price to the buying developer.</li> <li>There are costs and benefits in all of the various kinds of Seller-financing schemes:</li> </ul> <p>Seller financing; The seller lends the buyer the money to property. This also referred to as a purchase money mortgage.</p> <p>Option agreements:&nbsp;buyer&nbsp;acquires the right to purchase the property at a specified sometime some time in the future. Extension provisions can very important.</p> <p>Sales contract with conditions, pre-conditions to close: A sales contract can be used to control the property until&nbsp;certain condition are met prior to closing. Sales contract usually have non-refundable good faith deposits, and there are usually extension provisions in the contract.</p> <p>Lease with option to buy: Land leases allow the lessee (prospective buyer) to control the property (subject to the lease provisions), and the lease has provisions allowing the lessor to purchase the property at certain times during the lease term. The price of the property should be specified, but often it is not so the purchase price is at the market value or at a price mutually agreed upon between the lessor and the lessee.</p> <p>Land contracts: The land contract provides for the title to pass from the seller to the buyer after certain specific terms and conditions are met.&nbsp;</p> <p>Interim land uses: These can provide rental income to the land banker which help to defray the holding costs. These uses can be as simple as seasonal hunting lease or as complex as a long term commercial lease with termination provisions.</p> <p>Patient money is elusive but very important</p> <ul> <li>Land Bankers look for capital that is &ldquo;patient,&rdquo; that is it does not require immediate returns and is willing to wait for the eventual sale of the property when the market conditions are favorable.</li> <li>Patient money is not &ldquo;dumb money&rdquo; and the expected returns must justify the risks involved.</li> <li>Patient money is hard to find.</li> </ul> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162874/Financing%20in%20Land%20Packaging%20Stage">Financing in Land Packaging Stage</a></p>]]>
        </task>
        <task position="3">
            <![CDATA[<p>Market Studies &amp; Marketing Strategy &ndash; Land Banking (III.1.)</p> <p>The discussion of future trends should begin with the Charles Kettering quote,&rdquo; We should all be concerned about the future because we will spend the rest of our lives there.&rdquo; (Charles Kettering, 1876-1958, inventor, engineer, and businessman).</p> <p>Land banker must identify general and specific long term trends and determine how they will effect the attractiveness (demand for) a specific property.</p> <ul> <li>Identifying&nbsp;long-term trends is one thing, but interpreting those trends in terms of urban development and land use is much for difficult.&nbsp;Charles Kettering is also credited with the saying, &ldquo;The harder I work the luckier I get.&rdquo;&nbsp;</li> <li>&nbsp;The land banker must read widely and voraciously, looking for new ideas and insights into future real estate development opportunities.</li> </ul> <p>What kind of trends are we talking about?</p> <ul> <li>Demographic change</li> <li>Online shopping, education, commerce</li> <li>Robotics</li> <li>Health care and prevention</li> <li>Globalization</li> <li>Terrorism</li> <li>Climate Change</li> <li>Regulatory Environment</li> <li>Infrastructure Improvements</li> <li>Other&nbsp;trends?</li> <ul> <li>Recycling</li> <li>Immigration</li> <li>Renewable Energy technologies</li> <li>Transportation technologies</li> </ul> </ul> <p>Determine how will the general community and political establishment&nbsp;will&nbsp;react to those trends.</p> <ul> <li>Maintaining&nbsp;the&nbsp;status quo is a very strong force in communities.</li> <li>Economic change will cause new financial winner and losers. Who are they?</li> </ul> <p>When will the trends and the predicted effects occur?</p> <ul> <li>Change&nbsp;will occur, but when?</li> <ul> <li>During the land bankers holding period,&nbsp;</li> <li>Some land bankers have a very long holding period, some don&rsquo;t.</li> </ul> </ul> <p>Land Banker may focus on a particular event.</p> <ul> <li>Completion of a transit way and/or a transit station</li> <li>Completion of the Panama Canal widening and deepening</li> </ul> <p>Click below to go to the next Task vertically in the Matrix.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52166993/Market%20Studies%20and%20Marketing%20Strategies%20Land%20Packaging">Market Studies and Marketing Strategies Land Packaging</a></p> ]]>
        </task>
        <task position="4">
            <![CDATA[<p><strong>Phase I, II, and III Studies.</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Phase I&nbsp;&ndash; Survey of site conditions; review existing documents and inspection of the property</strong></li> <li><strong>Phase II&nbsp;&ndash; Testing of environmental site conditions. Determine existence of any regulated substances or suspicious conditions</strong></li> <li><strong>Phase III- Remediation of certain environmental conditions or objectionable substances.&nbsp;</strong></li> <li><strong>After Phase III a &ldquo;No further action letter&rdquo; is the goal.</strong></li> </ul> <p><strong>Certifications:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>U.S. Green Building Council &ndash; Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED)</strong></li> <li><strong>Green Globes</strong></li> <li><strong>Energy Star</strong></li> <li><strong>Building Owners and Managers Association - BOMA360</strong></li> <li><strong>Local/Regional Ordinances</strong></li> </ul> <p><strong>Surface conditions to consider: wetlands, rivers, abandoned mines,&nbsp;grave yards, geological formations.</strong></p> <ul> <li>Atmospheric examples:</li> <ul> <li>Sunlight, heat</li> <li>Wind</li> <li>Air pollution</li> </ul> <li>Surface examples:</li> <ul> <li>Flood Plains</li> <li>Wetlands</li> <li>Forestation</li> </ul> <li>Subsurface examples:</li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Water level or water table</li> <li>&nbsp;Soil Compaction</li> <li>&nbsp;Geological Strata&nbsp;</li> </ul> </ul> <p><strong>Historic and Cultural: research title and survey history.</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Are there historic events, cultural traditions, or religious considerations that can affect the development of the site?</strong></li> <li><strong>Some resources for this research include:</strong></li> <ul> <li><strong>Local historians</strong></li> <li><strong>Anthropologists</strong></li> <li><strong>Neighborhood activist groups&nbsp;</strong></li> <li><strong>Property archives and records</strong></li> </ul> </ul> <p>Click on the link below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52167770/Environmental%20Tasks%20in%20Land%20Development%20Stage">Environmental Tasks in Land Development Stage</a></p> <p>Edited with <a href="http://www.html-cleaner.com/" target="_blank">Online HTML Converter</a>.</p>]]>
        </task>
        <task position="5">
            <![CDATA[<p>Approvals and Permits &ndash; Land Banking (V.1.)</p> <ul> <li><strong>Agricultural zoning has many meanings.</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Wetlands are sacred, but substitution is possible.</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Flood plains have negotiated uses.</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Regional transportation plan, multi-modal, multi-access.</strong></li> <li><strong>Endangered species and historical events can restrict future development opportunities.</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Interim land use must be compatible and non-controversial.</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>The land bankers must research all of the existing restricted and permissible uses on their site.</strong></li> </ul> <p>Click on the link below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52167932/Approvals%20and%20Permits%20in%20Land%20Packaging%20Stage">Approvals and Permits in Land Packaging Stage</a></p>]]>
        </task>
        <task position="6">
            <![CDATA[<p>Improvements &ndash; Land Banking (VI.1.)</p> <p>Land Bankers create the &ldquo;concept plan.&rdquo;</p> <p><strong>Land bankers often plan and design improvements to help land packagers appreciate what can be done with the property, such as:</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;Roads and lots dealing with physical features.</p> <p> &bull;Road systems that tie into existing transportation routes.</p> <p> &bull;Amenities and common areas for future development.</p> <p> &bull;Location of on-site water treatment facilities and/or storm water management facilities.</p> <p> &bull;Environmental features which must be embraced or avoided..</p> <p><strong>Improvements for Interim land uses:</strong></p> <p> First do not harm!</p> <p> &bull;Maintain exiting&nbsp;road and drainage ditches.</p> <p> &bull;Maintain gates, fences and security systems.</p> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52168540/Improvements%20in%20the%20Land%20Packaging%20Stage">Improvements in the Land Packaging Stage</a> </p> ]]>
        </task>
        <task position="7">
            <![CDATA[<p>Transportation &amp; Accessibility &ndash; Land Banking (VII.1.)</p> <p><strong>Focus on&nbsp;future changes&nbsp;to&ldquo;big picture&rdquo; transportation systems:</strong></p> <p> &bull;Highways</p> <p> &bull;Railways: heavy and light rail</p> <p> &bull;Airports, seaports, and commercial railroad terminals</p> <p> &bull;Regional trails and pathways</p> <p><strong>Focus on &ldquo;property specific&rdquo; accessibility issues:</strong></p> <p> &bull;Ingress &ndash; getting into the property</p> <p> &bull;Egress &ndash; getting out of the property</p> <p> &bull;Getting around within the property</p> <p> &bull;Physical features</p> <p> &bull;Legal restrictions</p> <p><strong>Estimate the timeline for future transportation and accessibility improvements:</strong></p> <p> &bull;Current activity</p> <p> &bull;1-3 years;&nbsp;4-7 years; 8-10 years</p> <p> &bull;Estimate the probability of completion</p> <p><strong>Contact the appropriate governmental personnel and political figures about transportation and accessibility improvements:</strong></p> <p> &bull;Without their help and support, nothing will happen.</p> <p> &bull;Emphasize&nbsp;the benefits to the region.</p> <p> &bull;Evaluate their level of support.</p> <p><strong>Determine if additional land parcels are required:</strong></p> <p> &bull;Possible land assemblage opportunity</p> <p> &bull;Evaluate probability&nbsp;of current owners cooperating</p> <p><strong>Will the property be subject to Eminent Domain actions or restrictive easements or right-of-ways?</strong></p> <p> &bull;Eminent&nbsp;domain: government taking property at market value for a public use.</p> <p> &bull;Restrictive&nbsp;easements: regulations limit the use of the site.</p> <p> &bull;Avigation (or aviation) easements limiting the height of the buildings near airports.</p> <p> &bull;Noise regulation limiting the type of development around airport.</p> <p> &bull;Compensation is not always provided to impacted property owners.</p> <p> &bull;Right-of ways:&nbsp;governmental or quasi-government right to use (part of) the property but not to occupy it.</p> <p> &bull;Market value compensation to property owner. </p> <p> &bull;These takings can be an opportunity because it establishes the land banker as a stake holder in the transportation improvements.</p> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52161558/Transportation%20and%20Accessibility%20in%20Land%20Packaging">Transportation and Accessibility in Land Packaging</a></p> <p>Edited with <a href="http://www.html-cleaner.com/" target="_blank">Online HTML Converter</a>.</p>]]>
        </task>
        <task position="8">
            <![CDATA[<p>Disposition &ndash; Land Banking (VIII.1.)</p> <p><strong>Hold vs. Sell Decision:</strong></p> <p> &bull;What happens next year?</p> <ul> <ul> <li>To create additional value</li> <li>To&nbsp;decrease the existing value</li> </ul> </ul> <p> &bull;Reinvestment rate assumptions:</p> <ul> <ul> <li>What are the seller&rsquo;s reinvestment opportunities?</li> </ul> </ul> <p><strong>Determine if buyer can fulfill the contract condition(s).</strong></p> <p> &bull;Raise&nbsp;the required capital</p> <p> &bull;Non-refundable good faith deposit</p> <p> &bull;Due diligence review</p> <p><strong>Determine if certain public approvals are required prior to closing.</strong></p> <p> &bull;Annexation</p> <p> &bull;Zoning&nbsp;changes</p> <p> &bull;Interim use permits</p> <p> &bull;&ldquo;No further action letter&rdquo; from Environmental Protection Agency</p> <p><strong>Determine the seller&rsquo;s retained any liability.</strong></p> <p> &bull;Environmental liability</p> <p> &bull;Representation&nbsp;and Warranties about property condition</p> <p> &bull;On-going lawsuits</p> <p><strong>Determine what seller financing is available.</strong></p> <p> &bull;Purchase money mortgage</p> <p> &bull;Contract for sale with increasing good faith deposits</p> <p> &bull;Options</p> <p> &bull;Leases</p> <p> &bull;Land contract</p> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52159633/Sales%20and%20Disposition%20in%20Land%20Packaging">Sales and Disposition in Land Packaging</a></p>]]>
        </task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="2">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p><strong>Acquisitions &ndash; Land Packaging (I.2.)</strong></p> <p>Identify a property&nbsp;that meets (at least) one of the&nbsp;three opportunity categories.&nbsp;No problems; only opportunities. The land packager must be able to find properties that have a development issue or problems and fix that issue in a timely manner. This is why many land packagers have formal training in law , engineering, or land planning or have substantial experience in politics and government.</p> <ol> <li>Ready for development but improperly zoned.</li> </ol> <p>This is most common&nbsp;situation for the land packager. The land packager develops a conceptual land plan and set about getting that land plan approved by the appropriate governing bodies. These are usually zoning or planning commissions as well as city councils or county/township supervisory boards. The land packager must determine not only what approvals are needed , but also how to obtain those approvals in a timely manner.</p> <p> 2.Contains development impairments that can be remedied by studies, tests, and /or expert opinions.</p> <p>The land packager&nbsp;must correctly identify the development issues and then determine what experts can provide the information to clarify the problems or identify the best cost effective solutions to the problems. These problems may include wetland issues, contamination issues, soil and rock conditions, neighborhood concerns or protests, historical or cultural issues, or adjacent land issues such as railroads, airports, prisons, or coffee manufacturer.</p> <p> 3.Has existing title or survey issue.</p> <p>Most&nbsp;buyers avoid these kinds of problems, but with experience and special skills land packagers enjoy working out boundary issues, easement or right or way issues, existing liens, and clouds on the title. The timeliness and cost of fixing these issues is are the key factors for the land packager to assess. Almost any &ldquo;problem&rdquo; can be fixed with enough time and enough money., but the land packager cannot afford either.</p> <p>Evaluate if the regulatory environment&nbsp;is receptive to changing land use conditions.</p> <p>Clearly some&nbsp;municipalities and jurisdictions are easier to work in than others. However, know how the system or process works and who works the system is critical knowledge for the land packager. Perceived &ldquo;outsiders&rdquo; will bet treated much differently than known, credible, local people. The successful land packager will either need to be a &ldquo;good ol&rsquo; boy or gal&rdquo; or will be able to bring those people on her team.</p> <p>On the other hand, municipalities or jurisdictions that have a difficult reputation, are creating opportunities for land packagers because of the perceived &ldquo;barriers to entry&rdquo; that limit the number of competitive development. Land packager must critically evaluate their ability to work in the system and moor importantly to achieve permits and approvals in a timely manner.</p> <p><strong>Acquire or control the property with attractive prices and conditions.&nbsp;</strong> The important&nbsp;part is to control the property rather than to own the property outright. Creative financing often includes some of the following:</p> <p>Seller financing; The seller lends the buyer the money to property. This also referred to as a&nbsp;purchase money mortgage.</p> <p>Option agreements:&nbsp;buyer&nbsp;acquires the right to purchase the property at a specified sometime some time in the future. Extension provisions can very important</p> <p>Sales contract with conditions, pre-conditions to close: A sales contract can be used to control the property until&nbsp;certain condition are met prior to closing. Sales contract usually have non-refundable good faith deposits, and there are usually extension provisions in the contract.</p> <p>Lease with option to buy: land leases allow the lessee (prospective buyer) to control the property (subject to the lease provisions), and the lease has provisions allowing the lessor to purchase the property at certain times during the lease term. The price of the property should be specified, but often it is not so the purchase price is at the market value or at a price mutually agreed upon between the lessor and the lessee</p> <p><strong>Land contracts: </strong>The land contract provides for the title to pass from the seller to the buyer after certain specific terms and conditions are met.&nbsp;</p> <p>Interim land uses: These can provide rental income to the land banker which help to defray the holding costs. These uses can be as simple as seasonal hunting lease or as complex as a long term commercial lease with termination provisions.</p> <p>Are there&nbsp;interim land uses&nbsp;to be dealt with? (Positive or Negative?)</p> <p>Interim land uses are a two-edged sword. They can be very helpful in reducing the holding&nbsp;costs, and they can be very problematic in changing the use of the site or getting adjacent land owners to be cooperative.</p> <p>Click on the blue link below to move to the next block in the matrix horizontally.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162210/Acquisition%20Development%20Stage">Acquisition Development Stage</a></p> <p>Edited with <a href="http://www.html-cleaner.com/" target="_blank">Online HTML Converter</a>.</p>]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="3">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p><strong>Acquisitions &ndash; Land Development (I.3.)</strong></p> <p>Determine if a properly zoned and permitted property can be acquired and sold as subdivided, building-ready lots when the horizontal infrastructure is constructed.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;Land&nbsp;developer must use his:&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;legal team to estimate the appropriateness and firmness of the approval andpermits,</p> <p> &bull;marketing research and marketing team to estimate the salability and pricing of the finished lots.&nbsp;</p> <p>Determine if the required infrastructure improvements are known, defined, and priced.</p> <p> &bull;The&nbsp;land developer use his engineering and construction teams to estimate the &ldquo;feasibility &ldquo; of constructing the</p> <p> required infrastructure on time and on budget.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;If the infrastructure is not well defined, then the developer should not close on the property until it is.&nbsp;</p> <p>Determine if the market conditions will improve or remain steady during the construction and sellout period.</p> <p> &bull;If the proposed land development&nbsp;is financially feasible under the current market conditions, the developer need to</p> <p> determine the probability of the current conditions deteriorating.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;On the other hand, if the purposed land development is not financially feasible under the current market conditions, the</p> <p> developer must determine how much the current conditions need to improve. The developer is asking &ldquo;what has to</p> <p> change to make this deal work.&rdquo; </p> <p> &bull;If current market conditions are expected to improve, the critical determination is &ldquo;when&rdquo; will the conditions improve</p> <p> enough to make the project feasible.</p> <p>Determine if attractive pricing and terms be negotiated.</p> <p>Seller financing; The seller lends the buyer the money to property. This also referred to as a&nbsp;purchase money mortgage.</p> <p>Option agreements:&nbsp;buyer&nbsp;acquires the right to purchase the property at a specified sometime some time in the future. Extension provisions can very important</p> <p>Sales contract with conditions, pre-conditions to close: A sales contract can be used to control the property until&nbsp;certain condition are met prior to closing. Sales contract usually have non-refundable good faith deposits, and there are usually extension provisions in the contract.</p> <p>Lease with option to buy: land leases allow the lessee (prospective buyer) to control the property (subject to the lease provisions), and the lease has provisions allowing the lessor to purchase the property at certain times during the lease term. The price of the property should be specified, but often it is not so the purchase price is at the market value or at a price mutually agreed upon between the lessor and the lessee</p> <p>Land contracts: The land contract provides for the title to pass from the seller to the buyer after certain specific terms and conditions are met.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Interim land uses:</strong> These can provide rental income to the land banker which help to defray the holding costs. These uses can be as simple as seasonal hunting lease or as complex as a long term commercial lease with termination provisions.</p> <p>Estimate the sell-out period for the building ready pads prior to construction, during construction or after construction.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;The estimation of the&nbsp;land development period, from construction through final sell-out, is critical to determine the</p> <p> duration of the financing required for the development.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;A land development with several phases is very tricky since future phases should not become competition for the</p> <p> current phase.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;Multiple phase development usually&nbsp;last longer than the average business cycled (5-7 years). This means that the land</p> <p> developer must be prepared for variable market conditions and possibly devastating downside risks. </p> <p>Determine if the profit or &ldquo;spread&rdquo; is attractive enough to take the land development risks.</p> <p> &bull;The&nbsp;Land Developer must determine if the potential profits are worth the risks incurred. That is, is the &ldquo;spread&rdquo;</p> <p> between Development Costs and future sales prices attractive enough to undertake the projects.&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;The Land Developer must determine if there is a &ldquo;back door&rdquo; or a way out of the project if the market deteriorates too</p> <p> much.&nbsp;</p> <p>Determine the capital requirements.</p> <p> &bull;The land developer need determine:&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;how much capital is needed (uses of funds).</p> <p> &bull;who can provide the capital (sources of funds)&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;how long the capital is needed (investment duration)&nbsp;</p> <p> &bull;Equity investors are needed to acquire the land fund cash flow deficits during the development period.</p> <p> &bull;Construction loans are needed to fund some or all of the infrastructure construction costs.</p> <p> &bull;Short term loans (working capital loans) are needed to cover the funding gaps between the equity and construction</p> <p> loans.</p> <p>Here are some examples:</p> <p><a href="https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/potomac_yard_feasibility.pdf">https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/potomac_yard_feasibility.pdf</a></p> <p><a href="https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/potmomac_yard_acquisition_oct_2000.doc">https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/potmomac_yard_acquisition_oct_2000.do</a>c</p> <p><a href="https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/about_potomac_yard_03-21-01.doc">https://dankohlhepp.com/uploads/3/0/6/8/3068213/about_potomac_yard_03-21-01.doc</a> </p> <p>Click on the blue link below to move to the next block in the matrix horizontally.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162254/Acquisition%20Building%20Development%20Stage">Acquisition Building Development Stage</a></p>]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="4">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p>Acquisitions &ndash; Building Development (I.4.)</p> <p>The acquisition tasks for Building Development are very similar to the acquisition tasks for the Land Developer except that the Building Developer must be focused on estimating the probabilities of leasing the building while it is under construction as well as selling the property to a Building Operator.</p> <p>Determine if the building-ready pad can be acquired at a price that, when improved with the building, yields a required rate of return on total cost (Rtc).</p> <p>The Building Developer usually buys the finished lot with equity capital and intends to start construction the day of closing! Consequently,&nbsp;creative financing is not that important. However, the Building may negotiate certain terms in the purchase agreement that will prevent the Land Developer from impairing the competitiveness and profitability of the project. For example, the following provisions may be appropriate:</p> <ul> <li>Restrict the Land Developer&rsquo;s ability to sell lots&nbsp;to competitive projects for a certain period of time, say three years, or until the newly constructed building reaches a certain occupancy level.</li> <li>Provide a &ldquo;first right of offer&rdquo; to the Building Developer&nbsp;when additional lots are offered for sale.</li> <li>Estimate&nbsp;the Building Operators purchase price (based on overall capitalization rates) as well possible holdback that may be a condition of the sale. The Building Developer needs to pay off the construction loan at the time of sale so the hold backs cannot be too restrictive.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the building can be competitively bid by contractors and sub-contractor.</p> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Building&nbsp;developers usually have preferred general contractor and major sub-contractors. The availability of these firms is a critical determinant of when or if the Building&nbsp;Developer decides to acquire the building pad.</li> <li>Current pricing of the construction project is imperative because the Building Developer may be using old or inaccurate building costs estimates.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the property be pre-leased or leased up during construction.</p> <ul> <li>The best way for a Building Developer to create value is by pre-leasing&nbsp;the Building&nbsp;or leasing it up during construction.</li> <li>The Building&nbsp;Developer needs to understand the leasing market and develop a strategy to secure competitive leases</li> </ul> <p>Estimate if the current market conditions improve or remain steady during construction and lease-up</p> <ul> <li>If&nbsp;the current market conditions are good, how long will they last?</li> <li>If the current market conditions are bad, when will they change? We always recognize market bubbles after they occur, when it is too late to act.</li> <li>The Building&nbsp;Development period needs to include&nbsp;the pre-construction&nbsp;time, the building construction time, and the expected lease-up period.</li> </ul> <p>Determine the expected &ldquo;spread&rdquo; sufficient to justify the risk.</p> <ul> <li>Does&nbsp;the expected return justify the risks involved in the Building&nbsp;Development?</li> <li>The value created must be greater than the cost of the project so that the profit or spread is reward for the risk-taking.</li> </ul> <p>Estimate the capital requirements of the Building Development.</p> <ul> <li>The&nbsp;building&nbsp;developer need determine:&nbsp;</li> <ul> <li>how much capital is needed (uses of funds)</li> <li>who can provide the capital (sources of funds)</li> <li>how long the capital is needed (investment duration)</li> </ul> <li>Equity investors are needed to acquire the finished building lot and to fund cash flow deficits during the construction and lease-up period. These are usually the soft costs.</li> <ul> <li>Construction loans are needed to fund as much of the direct construction costs (the hard costs) as possible</li> <li>Construction loan extensions, often called mini-perms,&rdquo; are useful to manage the lease-up risks.</li> </ul> </ul> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162283/Acquisition%20Operating%20Stage">Acquisition Operating Stag</a>e</p>]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="5">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p>Acquisitions &ndash; Building Operations (I.5.)</p> <ul> <li>The Building Operator initially acquires the property from the Building Developer. However, after this initial acquisition the Building Developer may sell the building to another operator, and this may occur several time over the economic life of the property.&nbsp;</li> <li>Similarly, the Building Operator may acquire the property from the Building Renovator who has updated the property physically and re-marketed the property accordingly.</li> <li>The Building Operator needs a clear understanding of her investment objectives and strategy, so the acquisition of the property can be evaluated in the context of the overall investment portfolio strategy.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the constructed building can be acquired at an attractive price and terms (holdbacks).</p> <ul> <li>The acquisition of a newly constructed building from a Building Operator usually requires some or all of the following&nbsp;hold backs for unleased or unoccupied space:</li> <ul> <li>Tenant improvements</li> <li>Leasing commissions</li> <li>&nbsp;Economic earn outs.</li> </ul> <li>The vendor agreements and contracts should be transferable or cancellable as the case may be.</li> <li>All equipment warranties and guarantees should be transferred.</li> <li>The Building Developer and Renovator are not usually good candidates for seller financing because they need to pay of their own construction loans.</li> <li>If the seller is another building operator, there my be opportunities for a creative financing in the form of seller financing (purchase-money mortgages)&nbsp;or existing and assumable financing.</li> <li>Wrap-around mortgages&nbsp;are used when an existing&nbsp;mortgage is kept in place, and the seller makes a purchase-money mortgage that is equal to the existing mortgage plus and additional amount. The seller, who is now the wrap around lender, makes the payments on the existing mortgage while the buyer, now the wraparound borrow, maonly one payment to the wraparound lender.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the property can be leased at expected rent levels (price &amp; occupancy) during the lease-up period.</p> <ul> <li>The Building Operator must estimate the probability of achieving&nbsp;both the rental rates and the occupancy level during the lease-up period. This may include the provision of inducements such as free-rent, additional tenant improvements, or moving costs reimbursements.</li> <li>The Building Developer must also assess the risk of re-leasing the property when existing tenants move out.</li> </ul> <p>Estimate if current market conditions will remain steady or improve during the expected lease-up and holding period.</p> <ul> <li>Of course the market conditions will change during the Building Operators expected holding period, but the question is whether the changes will increase or decrease the property&rsquo;s value.&nbsp;</li> <li>Regional economic forecasts must be considered and evaluated.</li> <li>New and existing competitive properties must be identified and evaluated.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the building operations and technologies are efficient. (Identify areas of improvement).</p> <ul> <li>Building commissioning is a requirement for newly constructed buildings that are seeking a LEED certification.</li> <li>Building commissioning confirms that all of the building operational systems are correctly installed and operating appropriately.</li> <li>Every meter and monitoring device is checked for accuracy. This commissioning activity is all done prior to occupancy. This is a major improvement over the good old days when new building systems were testing and balance during the early stages of operation and occupancy.</li> <li>Building operators who are acquiring existing building from other building operators must verify the operational efficiency as seeks out area that can be improved.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the expected tenants will flourish in the new building.</p> <ul> <li>Building operators must determine if the current tenants or the prospective tenants&nbsp;will be successful businesses in the building.</li> <li>To some extent, the Building Operators must underwrite the business plans of the tenants and determine if they are right for the building.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>Determine if the expected financing terms can be improved over time.</p> <ul> <li>The Building&nbsp;Operator&nbsp;must&nbsp;underwrite the acquisition in terms of the best capital structure for the property that include both debt and equity capital.</li> <li>The Building Operator must be forward looking to determine how the capital structure can be improved in the future.</li> </ul> <p> &bull;Lower interest rate</p> <p> &bull;Long amortization periods</p> <p> &bull;Longer term loans</p> <p> &bull;Consolidate loans</p> <p> &bull;Lower Debt Coverage Ratios</p> <p> &bull;Higher Loan to Value Ratios</p> <p> &bull;New equity investors with lower return expectations</p> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162314/Acquisition%20Renovation%20Stage">Acquisition Renovation Stage</a></p>]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="6">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p>Acquisitions &ndash; Building Renovations (I.6.)</p> <p><strong>Building Renovator are the most savvy and creative market analysts in the real estate development process:</strong></p> <p>&bull;They see trends developing before others.</p> <p>&bull;They know and understand the special needs of certain kinds of tenants.</p> <p>&bull;They identify and pre-lease to tenants who are ready to move to better or different space.</p> <p>Evaluate the current market conditions for pricing anomalies or niche opportunities.</p> <p>&bull;Determine if the rent differentials between various submarkets are&nbsp;justified in light of changing market conditions.</p> <p>&bull;Are certain users being ignored such as start-up companies, technology companies, or companies with special occupancy issues such a security or communications.</p> <p>Determine if the subject property be acquired, renovated, and repositioned to meet the market opportunities.</p> <p>&bull;The&nbsp;subject property are often overlooked properties in quirky locations.</p> <p>&bull;The current owners may not be aware of market opportunities.</p> <p>&bull;The anticipated renovation improvements must be defined and accurately priced.</p> <p>&bull;The market perception of the property must be changed during the renovation period.&nbsp;</p> <p>Determine if the renovation can be completed in a timely manner.</p> <p>&bull;A ready and available renovator contractor is a must.</p> <p>&bull;Government approvals and permits must&nbsp;be forthcoming.</p> <p>&bull;Neighborhood issues must be readily resolvable.&nbsp;</p> <p>Develop a strategy to deal with holdover tenants.</p> <p>&bull;Identify existing tenants who will remain in occupancy&nbsp;during the renovation period.</p> <p>&bull;Determine if their business needs as well as health and safety can be met and insure during the renovation period.</p> <p>&bull;Evaluate how the holdover tenants will fit in the marketing and leasing of the renovated building.</p> <p>&bull;Can the holdover tenants be moved to another location during the renovation period?&nbsp;</p> <p>Determine if the &ldquo;spread&rdquo; is large enough to justify the risks incurred.</p> <p>&bull;The building renovation is very risky.</p> <p>&bull;May be ahead of the market.</p> <p>&bull;May discover unexpected environmental, cultural, or historical issues.</p> <p>&bull;May have difficulty integrating new building construction and building systems into the existing building.</p> <p>&bull;May have unexpected issues with holdover tenants.</p> <p>&bull;Do the expected profits justify incurring these risks?</p> <p>Convince lenders and equity investors to support the planned renovations.</p> <p>&bull;Many&nbsp;times local lenders and equity investors do not share the vision of the Building Renovator.</p> <p>&bull;The best way to convince these skeptics of the validity of the new vision is with a pre-lease or a pre-sale.</p> <p>&bull;Of course, a successful track record in building renovations is the best way to win support and attract the necessary capital.&nbsp;</p> <p>Click below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/52162378/Acquisition%20in%20Redevelopment%20Stage">Acquisition in Redevelopment Stage</a></p> ]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
    <stage position="7">
        <task position="1">
            <![CDATA[<p>Acquisitions &ndash; Property Redevelopment (I.7.)</p> <p>The Acquisition tasks in the Property Redevelopment Stage are very similar to the Acquisitions Task in the Land Banking Stage except that the proposed redevelopment property has a history of land uses and improvements while the land banking property is undeveloped in the sense its current use is agriculture, timber, or recreational open space. The land banking property does not have a history of urban uses (old shopping malls) of intensive vertical development (old paper mill)</p> <p>Determine if the property can be acquired at an attractive price and terms that allows for holding the property until it is ready for repackaging.</p> <ul> <li>Municipalities usually have a redevelopment agency or authority or a corporation that acts as the Property Redevelopment for the municipality. It&rsquo;s job is to take contrail of the properties that the municipality has obtained though tax foreclosures and in that role it tries to find a land packager to acquire the property or at least take control of the property as it goes through the re-zoning process.&nbsp;Other property redevelopers may be corporation that have abandoned or unused facilities that they would like to sell as excess property.</li> <li>&nbsp;Property redevelopers may be opportunistic individuals that are convinced that a property will soon be ready to be re-zoned for a new economic life.</li> <li>&nbsp;The opportunistic redevelopers may have opportunities to negotiate acquisition terms that minimize the upfront cost as well as holding costs:</li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Seller financing; The seller lends the buyer the money to property. This also referred to as a&nbsp;purchase money mortgage.</li> <li>&nbsp;Option agreements:&nbsp;buyer acquires the right to purchase the property at a specified sometime some time in the future. Extension provisions can very important.</li> <li>&nbsp;Sales contract with conditions, pre-conditions to close: A sales contract can be used to control the property until certain condition are met prior to closing. Sales contracts usually have non-refundable good faith deposits, and there are usually extension provisions in the contract.</li> <li>&nbsp;Lease with option to buy: land leases allow the lessee (prospective buyer) to control the property (subject to the lease provisions), and the lease has provisions allowing the lessor to purchase the property at certain times during the lease term. The price of the property should be specified, but often it is not so the purchase price is at the market value or at a price mutually agreed upon between the lessor and the lessee.</li> <li>&nbsp;Land contracts: The land contract provides for the title to pass from the seller to the buyer after certain specific terms and conditions are met.</li> <li>&nbsp;Interim land uses: These can provide rental income to the land banker which help to defray the holding costs. These uses can be as simple as seasonal hunting lease or as complex as a long term commercial lease with termination provisions.</li> </ul> </ul> <p>Determine what external events need to occur to improve the attractiveness of the property:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Population growth</li> <li>Transportation improvements</li> <li>Technology changes</li> <li>Sustained regional&nbsp;economic growth</li> <li>Changed land use regulations</li> <li>Construction of transportation improvement</li> <li>Infrastructure capacity improvements</li> </ul> <p>Evaluate the political and governmental supportive of the redevelopment.</p> <ul> <li>Determine the current support for redeveloping the property and/or the area.</li> <li>&nbsp;Develop a strategy in increase their support.</li> </ul> <p>Determine if &ldquo;de-commissioning&rdquo; the property will increase its attractiveness.</p> <ul> <li>Demolishing existing improvements may improve the market&rsquo;s opinion of the properties potential.</li> <li>&nbsp;Removing obnoxious or toxic material may improve the property redevelopment potential.</li> </ul> <p>Confirm that the public&rsquo;s health and safety be assured during the redevelopment stage.</p> <ul> <li>The redevelopment property may be part of a blighted area or urban waste land.</li> <li>Can fencing, gates, or alarm systems be installed to prohibit people from entering the property?</li> <li>If the property is a public health of safety hazard, the property redeveloper should determine how to mitigate these risks and how much the mitigation plan will cost.</li> </ul> <p>Find a &ldquo;back door&rdquo; if the redevelopment potential never materializes.</p> <p> &bull;Before acquiring the property, the redeveloper must have a plan to sell the property.</p> <p> &bull;If things go well, the redeveloper will sell the property to a land packager.</p> <p> &bull;If things don&rsquo;t go well, the redeveloper need to have a &ldquo;back door&rdquo; out of the deal.</p> <p> &bull;Cancellation of the purchase contract, or option contract.</p> <p> &bull;Default and foreclosure on purchase money mortgages.</p> <p> &bull;Donation to a charity or non-profit.</p> <p> &bull;Long-term &ldquo;interim&rdquo; land use.</p> <p>Click on the blue link below to move to the next Task in the Matrix .</p> <p><a href="http://jhuesjrealestateprogram.pbworks.com/w/page/67477527/Financing%20in%20Land%20Banking">Financing in Land Banking</a></p> <p>Edited with <a href="http://www.html-cleaner.com/" target="_blank">Online HTML Converter</a>.</p>]]></task>
        <task position="2"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="3"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="4"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="5"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="6"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="7"><![CDATA[]]></task>
        <task position="8"><![CDATA[]]></task>
    </stage>
</matrix>