<headers>
    <header type="stage">
        <node>
            <title>Land Banking</title>
            <content>The “Land Banker” acquires or holds undeveloped or “raw” that he believes will become attractive
                for future development through general and broad market trends or perhaps. Land bankers can be active in
                the pursue the acquisiton of opportunistic “land buys”. Although many land bankers can be advertant land
                owners such as estates or government agencies or public utilities. This is a relatively passive
                investment position. Good examples of “land bankers” are public utilities, universities, and inheritors
                of the “family farm.” When the market conditions are right, the land banker then sells the land to a
                “land packager”.
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Land Packaging</title>
            <content>The “Land Packager” buys the raw land from the passive land banker and then improves the value of
                the land through conceptual land planning, zoning changes, financing schemes, or other “paper
                enhancements” like title insurance, accurate surveys, or environmental studies. Examples of land
                packagers are land planning firms, politically skilled lawyers, and governmental agencies who attempt to
                obtain government approvals of land they own. This “packaged land” is then sold to the “land developer.”
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Land Development</title>
            <content>The “Land Developer” buys the land with the paper enhancements from the land packager and then
                improves the land so it can be sold as finished building pads to building developer. This usually
                involves the construction of horizontal infrastructure such as roads and utilities as well as common
                improvements such as water dentition ponds and recreational facilities. A good example of the land
                developers are master-planned community developers who construct the roads, utilities, and recreational
                amenities and then sell building lots to home builders.
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Building Development</title>
            <content>The “Building Developer” buys the finished pad from the land developer and then does the vertical
                development by constructing the building improvements. During construction, the building developer may
                also attempt to lease the building so the finished building can be sold to the building operator. Home
                builders are a good example of building developers. On the commercial side, building developers are
                often called “merchant builders.”
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Building Operations</title>
            <content>The “Building Operator” leases up the property, manages the property, and develops a building
                operating history so it can be sold to other building operators during its economic life or sold to a
                building renovator at the end of its economic life. The biggest building operators are usually referred
                to as institutional investors which may include pension funds, insurance companies, or public real
                estate investment trusts.
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Building Renovation</title>
            <content>The “Building Renovator” buys the property with substantial economic and/or physical depreciation
                and creates value by curing these deficiencies then re-positioning and operating the building until the
                property is ready for redevelopment. The unique skills and risks for building renovators are usually
                found in companies that specialize in “historic renovation.” Currently, many shopping center developers
                are looking for old centers that need to be fixed-up and re-marketed to different retail tenants.
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Property Redevelopment</title>
            <content>The “Property Re-developer” buys the property with such serious physical or functional deficiencies
                that the improvements must be torn down and/or re-developed for another use. This essentially begins the
                real estate development process all over again. Essentially this is the same role as the "land banker"
                except that a land banker usually works with "green field" properties and the redeveloper usually works
                with "brown field" properties. In every major city, government-sponsored redevelopment agencies are
                probably the largest players in the stage even though they didn’t exactly “buy” their holdings from
                building renovators. Usually the municipalities acquire the properties through tax foreclosures and
                assign these properties to the redevelopment agencies to be sold.
            </content>
            <image>/imsages/landbanking.png</image>
        </node>
    </header>
    <header type="task">
        <node>
            <title>Acquisition</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>Each stage of development begins with the <strong>Acquisition Tasks</strong>.<strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">&nbsp;</strong><span>Often the Acquisition Tasks are broken down into five categories: feasibility studies, underwriting requirements, contract negotiations, and closing conditions.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5;">Feasibility:&nbsp; Do the anticipated future benefits exceed the expected future costs?</strong></li> <ul> <li>Physical and engineering feasibility:</li> <ul> <li>Properties physical characteristics</li> <li>Cost to build whatever? </li> </ul> <li>Market feasibility:</li> <ul> <li>Current market conditions&nbsp;</li> <li>Future market conditions </li> </ul> <li>Financial feasibility:</li> <ul> <li>Simple Measures of Profitability </li> <li>Complex measures of Profitability </li> </ul> <li>Do the anticipated future benefits exceed the expected future costs?<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5;">Underwriting:&nbsp; Can capital be attracted to this development given the risk and returns of the development?</strong></li> <ul> <li>Required Rates of Returns</li> <li>&nbsp;How much capital?</li> <li>&nbsp;Who has this capital? </li> <li>How long is the capital needed?</li> </ul> <li><strong>Contract:&nbsp;&nbsp; How is title, control, monies, and associated risks transferred from the seller to the buyer?</strong></li> <ul> <li>The purchase contract defines how the title, control, monies, and associated risks are transferred from the seller to the buyer. </li> <ul> <li>What rights are being transferred? </li> <li>What representations and warranties are being made? </li> <li>To whom; from whom? </li> <li>Conditions to close? (Pre-closing conditions) </li> <li>Deadlines, milestones, deposits? </li> <li>Post-closing conditions?<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> </ul> <li><strong>Due Diligence:&nbsp; Are the assumptions about development (legal, physical, economic, market) valid or have they been verified?</strong></li> <ul> <li><strong>Confirm that the assumptions about future development (legal, physical, financial, market) are valid and have been verified? </strong></li> <ul> <li><strong>Multi-disciplinary exercise </strong></li> <li><strong>No &ldquo;limiting assumptions&rdquo; &ndash;No excuses </strong></li> </ul> <li><strong>&bull;Confirm that there is a reasonable possibility that this acquisition will meet or exceed the buyer&rsquo;s development expectations and investment objectives. </strong></li> <li><strong>Ideally, the due diligence is performed before the good faith deposit become non-refundable&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <li><strong>Closing:&nbsp; Have all of the required conditions to close been met, and have all of the required documents been prepared, reviewed, and executed?</strong></li> <ul> <li>All of the required conditions to close must be met.</li> <li>&nbsp;All of the required documents have been prepared, reviewed, and executed.</li> <li>The capital is ready to be transferred.</li> <li>The post-closing obligations (development agreements) have been defined, documented, and guaranteed<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Click below to move to the first Stage.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="/w/page/52011243/Acquisition%20Tasks%20in%20Land%20Banking">Acquisition Tasks in Land Banking</a></p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Financing</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>The <strong>F</strong><span><strong>inancing Tasks</strong> require the developer to determine the amount and type of capital required to fund the initial acquisition, the interim holding costs,&nbsp; the completion of the required tasks, and eventual disposition of the development.&nbsp; The developer then must determine &nbsp;the most efficient method to raise the required capital and then to actually raise the capital.&nbsp; The financing tasks can be divided in to three categories: financial projections, financial management and projections, and capital formation and accumulation.</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Projections:&nbsp; What are the amounts and timing of expected capital expenditures, holding costs, and operating expenses as well as sales, rents, and<span>&nbsp;other income?</span></strong></li> <ul> <li>Determine are the amounts and timing of expected capital expenditures, holding costs, and operating expenses as well as sales, rents, and other income.</li> <li>&nbsp;Stabilized pro-formas aren&rsquo;t enough.</li> <li>Negative cash flows are fatal! (Reserves, reserves, reserves)</li> <li>Accurate estimates of annual cash flows are needed for the real estate enterprise to create value.</li> <li>Financing structures must support and complement the real estate enterprise activities.<span>&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> <li><strong>Financial management and reporting:&nbsp; How will the future capital flows be managed and to whom and in what form will they be reported?</strong></li> <ul> <li>Future capital flows must be managed, funded, distributed, and reported&nbsp; in a timely manner. </li> <li>General Rule: good real estate projects have good accounting; bad real estate projects have bad accounting</li> <li>Determine who will keep the books, disburse the funds, collect the rents, and prepare the reports. </li> <li>Who gets reports? </li> <ul> <li>IRS </li> <li>State Department of Taxation </li> <li>Equity Investors (sometimes Debt Investors too) </li> <li>Asset Managers </li> <li>Property Managers </li> <li>Others? (Certifications, professional groups, marketing) </li> </ul> <li>Establish annual budgets: report actual versus budget with variances&nbsp;</li> </ul> <li><strong>Capital formation and accumulation:&nbsp; Given the risk, returns, and timing of the capital flows of the development, what is the appropriate capital s<span>tructure and sources and how can it be secured?</span></strong></li> <ul> <li>Financing must support the real estate enterprise!</li> <li>Interest rate: Fixed rate vs. variable rate</li> <li>Long-term, fixed rate fixed payment mortgage is only appropriate for building operations.</li> <li>Long term capital vs. short term capital </li> <li>Seller financing</li> <li>Equity investors<strong><span>&nbsp;</span></strong></li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="/w/page/52162906/Financing%20in%20Land%20Development%20Stage">Financing in Land Development Stage</a></p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Market Studies and Marketing Strategies</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>he <strong>Marketing &nbsp;Tasks </strong>require the developer to determine what are the current and future market conditions for the expected end-uses(ers)&nbsp; of the property.&nbsp; The developer then must determine the most appropriate marketing strategy given the current and future market conditions.&nbsp; In implementing the marketing strategy,&nbsp; the developer must determine the appropriate marketing mix.<strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong>The marketing tasks can be broken down into three categories:&nbsp; projected economic conditions, market strategy, and advertising and promotion (the marketing mix).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Projected Market Conditions:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine what land uses should be developed on the site.</span></li> <ul> <li><span style="font-weight: bold; line-height: 1.2em;">&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Highest and Best Use.</span>Graaskamp says this should be the most &ldquo;acceptable use.&rdquo;</li> <li>&nbsp;<span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Future Market Demand</span></li> <li><span>Future Competitive Supply</span></li> </ul> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine when the land uses should be brought to market (absorption).</span></li> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Construction time</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Absorption time</span></li> </ul> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine how and by whom the land uses should&nbsp; be brought to market.</span></li> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">In-house marketing and sales</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Out-of-house marketing and sales (brokers, auctions, etc.)</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">In house &amp; out-of-house combination</span></li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">Market Strategies:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li>What amount of various land uses should be developed on the site?</li> <li>How and by whom should they be brought to market?</li> <li>The best ways to determine the current and future market conditions is to:</li> <ul> <li>Read, Read, Read (everything that you can find):</li> <ul> <li>National &amp; regional publications (Newspapers, magazines)<span> </span></li> <li>Local newsletters (on-line discussions of the regional and local economy<span> </span></li> <li>Online market surveys are produced by:<span> </span></li> <ul> <li>National and Regional Brokerage Firms<span> </span></li> <li>National and Regional market research firms<span> </span></li> <ul> <li>CoStar</li> <li>Xcligent<span> </span></li> <li>Loopnet<span> </span></li> </ul> </ul> </ul> <li>Personally Network with local human beings such as:<span> </span></li> <ul> <li><span>&nbsp;</span>Brokers<span> </span></li> <li><span>&nbsp;</span>Business leaders<span> </span></li> <li><span>&nbsp;</span>Politicians and government officials</li> </ul> </ul> </ul> <p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>Promotion and Advertising:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine to whom the development be promoted and advertised.</span></li> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Who is the target buyer/renter?</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">What is the best way to approach the target audience?</span><span>&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine the sales pitch and who should make it.</span></li> <ul> <li>Need a consistent theme.</li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Easily understood and presented.</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">General property promotion to the community and neighborhood.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Specific property promotion to motivated and capable buyers/renters.</span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine the appropriate marketing mix&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">(events, promotional materials, electronic advertising, site visits, etc.)</span></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><a href="/w/page/52167033/Marketing%20Studies%20and%20Marketing%20Strategies%20in%20Land%20Development%20Stage">Marketing Studies and Marketing Strategies in Land Development Stage</a> &nbsp;</p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Environmental Studies</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p><span>Phase I, II, and III Studies.</span></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"><span>Phase I&nbsp;&ndash; Survey of site conditions; review existing documents and inspection of the property </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"><span>Phase II&nbsp;&ndash; Testing of environmental site conditions. Determine existence of any regulated substances or suspicious conditions </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"><span>Phase III- Remediation of certain environmental conditions or objectionable substances.&nbsp;</span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"><span>After Phase III a &ldquo;No further action letter&rdquo; is the goal. </span></strong></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"><span>Certifications:&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-size: 115%; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>U.S. Green Building Council &ndash; Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED) </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-size: 115%; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Green Globes </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-size: 115%; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Energy Star</span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-size: 115%; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Building Owners and Managers Association - BOMA360 </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-size: 115%; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Local/Regional Ordinances</span></strong></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Surface conditions to consider: wetlands, rivers, abandoned mines,&nbsp;grave yards, geological formations.</span></p> <ul> <li>Atmospheric examples: </li> <ul> <li>Sunlight, heat </li> <li>Wind </li> <li>Air pollution</li> </ul> <li>Surface examples:</li> <ul> <li>Flood Plains</li> <li>Wetlands </li> <li>Forestation</li> </ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Subsurface </span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">examples:</span></li> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Water level or water table</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;"> </span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Soil Compaction</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Geological Strata&nbsp;</span></li> </ul> </ul> <p><span>Historic and Cultural: research title and survey history.</span></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Are there historic events, cultural traditions, or religious considerations that can affect the development of the site? </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Some resources for this research include: </span></strong></li> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Local historians </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Anthropologists </span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Neighborhood activist groups&nbsp;</span></strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;"><span>Property archives and records</span></strong></li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Click on the link below to move to the next Stage.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="/w/page/52167770/Environmental%20Tasks%20in%20Land%20Development%20Stage">Environmental Tasks in Land Development Stage</a></p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Approvals and Permits</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p><span>In every stage that there are the required approvals and permits needed to operate , improve, or modify the property during the development.&nbsp; The developer must not only determine what approvals and permits are necessary, but he must also acquire these approval and permits in a timely and cost effective manner.&nbsp; The approvals may be at the federal, state or municipal level and they also may be from regional authorities or private individuals or organizations.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><strong>Developers must realize and accept the natural tension that occurs during this process.</strong></span></p> <ul> <li>Natural Tension Occurs: </li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Between private and public ownership rights.</li> <li>&nbsp;Between federal, state, regional, and local governments.</li> <li>&nbsp;Between various departments and commissions within a government.</li> <li>Between adjacent land uses (neighbors).</li> </ul> <li>&nbsp;Every stage of the real estate development process requires some kind of governmental, quasi-governmental, or private approvals and/or permits.&nbsp;</li> <li>&nbsp;Remember: Real estate is a public good</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><strong>Developers must communicate with and understand the various individuals and agencies involved.</strong></span></p> <ul> <li>Don&rsquo;t fight, make friends.</li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;No one is going away.</li> </ul> <li>&nbsp;Find areas of agreement.</li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Understand your needs and the needs of others.</li> </ul> <li>Structure workable compromises.</li> <ul> <li>Win-win solutions are imperative.</li> </ul> <li>Find timely resolutions.</li> <ul> <li>Time wounds all deals.</li> <li>Einstein once said, "The most powerful force in the world is compound interest."</li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><strong>Developers must expect, and prepare for: </strong></span></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">The worst: </strong></li> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">delays</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;"> loss of confidentiality</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">solicitation.</strong></li> </ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">&nbsp;</strong>To have prior agreements or understanding retracted or rebuked..</li> <li>To have confidential information made public.</li> <li>To address social and community problems that the developer cannot solve.</li> <li>To appreciate a variety of points of view that may at first seem illogical or irrelevant.</li> <li>To appreciate the perceived realities of various stakeholders.</li> <li>To reject illegal, inappropriate, and questionable offers in the name of &ldquo;finding a solution.&rdquo;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><strong>Developers must evaluate approvals and permits required at all public levels:</strong></span></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">federal</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">state</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">regional</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">municipal</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">private</strong></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a style="font-size: 13px; line-height: 1.5em;" href="/w/page/52167966/Approvals%20and%20Permits%20in%20Land%20Development%20Stage">Approvals and Permits in Land Development Stage</a><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Physical Improvements</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>The <strong>Improvement Tasks</strong> require the developer to determine what improvement (public or private; horizontal or vertical) need to be planned, designed, engineered, and construction.&nbsp; With that determination, the developer must be able to&nbsp; plan, design, engineer and or construct these improvements in a timely efficient and cost-effective manner.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Planning and design:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine if the desired,&nbsp; permitted, or required improvements can be built on or&nbsp; in the space allocated for those improvements, i.e., can you put 10 pounds of sugar in a 5- pound bag?</li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine if the desired improvements can be designed to meet market standards of&nbsp; acceptability.</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Determine if the talents of&nbsp; the requisite planners and architects are available to the developer.</span></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">Engineering:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li>Can the planned or designed improvements be built in an attractive, timely, and cost-effective manner?</li> <li>Can the planned or designed improvement be engineered to meet the current and future standards for sustainability and safety?</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Construction:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li>Can the improvements be built on-time and on budget?&nbsp;</li> <li>Are the&nbsp; general&nbsp; and sub-contractors available to take on this project?</li> <li>Are the necessary materials available and affordable?</li> </ul> <p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>Maintenance:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine how the constructed improvement will be maintained and operated in good working order over the life cycle of the improvements.</li> <li>&nbsp;Determine if the appropriate vendors are available to maintain and operate the improvements over their life .</li> <li>&nbsp;Establish&nbsp; appropriate reserves for future repairs and/or replacements.</li> <li>&nbsp;Warranties and Guarantees?&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="/w/page/52168597/Improvements%20in%20the%20Building%20Development%20Stage">Improvements in the Building Development Stage</a></p>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Transportation and Accessability</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>The <strong>Transportation and A</strong><span><strong>ccessibility Tasks</strong> require the developer to determine not only what transportation systems (public and private) the space users (tenants, customers, suppliers) will use to get to the property, but also to determine how &nbsp;tenants, customers, and suppliers will get around the site once they have reached it.&nbsp; In some cases these off-site transportation systems and in all cases the on-site accessibility&nbsp; systems&nbsp; must be designed, engineered, and constructed.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Off-Site: Transportation</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">Evaluate the existing transportation systems available to bring people and goods to the property&nbsp;.</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">Determine what changes or improvements to those systems are required to improve bringing goods and people to the site..</strong></li> <li><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">&nbsp;Evaluate if these changes or improvements can be permitted, designed and constructed in a timely and cost effective manner.</strong></li> </ul> <p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.5em;">&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>On-Site: Accessibility</strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine how will goods and services and people will&nbsp; access their destination once they arrive on site.</li> <li>Determine if roads, trails, walkways, elevators, escalators, and storage areas are adequate to handle the expected traffic among buildings and within buildings.</li> <li>Determine if these accessibility improvements &nbsp;can be designed and constructed in a timely and cost-effective manner.</li> <li>Determine the priorities of&nbsp; what must be accessible:</li> <ul> <li>Parking</li> <li>Building entrances</li> <li>Waste removal </li> <li>Mail and freight</li> <li>Suite entrances </li> <li>Emergency accessways and life-safety facilities and systems &nbsp;</li> </ul> </ul> <p><strong>On &amp; Off &ndash; Site: Construction</strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine required&nbsp; public approval and permits.</li> <li>&nbsp;Evaluate if Transportation &amp; Accessibility improvements can be built on-time and on budget:</li> <ul> <li>general and sub-contractors </li> <li>limited capacity/availability during the building season </li> </ul> <li>Determine if the necessary building materials are available and affordable.</li> <li>Evaluate the availability of public funding sources to finance roads, terminals, walkways, etc. </li> <li>Evaluate the effect of state, regional, or municipal tax subsidies for funding transportation and accessibility improvements.</li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>On &amp; Off &ndash; Site: </strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine how the constructed transportation and accessibility improvement will be maintained and operated in good working order over their life cycle.</li> <li>Identify the appropriate vendors available to maintain and operated the transportation and accessibility improvements.</li> <li>Establish appropriate reserves for future repairs and/or replacement.</li> <li>Clearly define and assign maintenance responsibilities.</li> <li>Define and distribute emergency plans.</li> </ul>]]></content>
        </node>
        <node>
            <title>Sales and Disposition</title>
            <content>
                <![CDATA[<p>The <strong>Sales and Disposition Tasks</strong> require the developer to complete the seller&rsquo;s due diligence, to market the property for sale, to negotiate and execute a sales contract and finally to negotiate any necessary development agreements.&nbsp; The developer may decide not to sell the property at this stage and continue on to the next stage of development. In this case, the disposition exercise is then blended in to the acquisition stage for the subsequent stage of development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Seller&rsquo;s Due Diligence:</strong></p> <ul> <li>What do we have?</li> <ul> <li>Physical description</li> <li>&nbsp;Legal description </li> <li>Economic description&nbsp;</li> </ul> <li>What is it worth?</li> <ul> <li>Direct sales approach </li> <li>&nbsp;<span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Replacement cost</span></li> <li>Income approach&nbsp;</li> </ul> <li>Who wants to buy it?</li> <ul> <li>Investors </li> <li>Users </li> <li>Other developers&nbsp;</li> </ul> <li>How do we effect a sale?</li> <ul> <li>Purchase Price </li> <li>Agreement terms &amp; conditions&nbsp;</li> </ul> </ul> <p><strong>Marketing:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Determine how the property should be presented to potential, qualified buyers:</li> <ul> <li>Targeted versus broad/spray marketing </li> <li>Internal/external brokers.</li> <li>&nbsp;Timeline </li> </ul> <li>Develop an appropriate pricing strategy.</li> <li>&nbsp;Consider seller financing possibilities:</li> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Purchase options</li> <li>Purchase-money mortgage</li> <li>Land contract</li> </ul> <li>Determine what risks, if any, the selling developer will retain.</li> <li>Determine how competitive buyers will be treated.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong style="color: #000000; font-family: inherit; font-size: 115%; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.2em;">Sales Contract:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Price and terms</li> <ul> <li>Representations and Warranties </li> </ul> <li>Conditions to close </li> <ul> <li>Buyer's due diligence period </li> <li>Good faith deposit</li> <li>Document preparation and review </li> <li>Title and survey resolution </li> <li>Public approvals </li> <li>Timing </li> <li>Tax Deferred Exchange requirements</li> </ul> <li>Post-closing conditions&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Development Agreements:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li>Development agreements allow land developer to sell almost finished land bays as finished land bay prices because of the binding Development Agreement that are executed at closing.&nbsp; These agreement protect the building developers because they address the following:</li> <ul> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">What must occur? (construction specifications)</span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">When must they occur?&nbsp; (milestones)</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;"> </span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">What happens when they don&rsquo;t occur? (guarantees, self-help, bonds)</span><span style="line-height: 1.2em;"> </span></li> <li><span style="line-height: 1.2em;">Multiple buyers predicament</span></li> </ul> </ul> <p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>Closing:</strong>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>When and where does closing occur? </li> <li>When does title pass? </li> <ul> <li><span style="font-weight: bold;">Title</span> from buyer to seller </li> <li>When does <span style="font-weight: bold;">Rent</span> become the property of the buyer? </li> <li>When does <span style="font-weight: bold;">Insurance</span> take effect for the buyer? </li> <li>When does <span style="font-weight: bold;">Liability </span>transfer from seller to buyer? </li> <li>When do <span style="font-weight: bold;">Obligations</span> transfer?</li> </ul> <li>When and how are cash funds transferred? </li> <ul> <li>Capital to Buyer </li> <li>Buyer to Seller</li> <li>Seller to Investors/Lenders </li> </ul> <li>Who is notified and when? </li> <ul> <li>Tenants </li> <li>IRS </li> <li>Municipality/Utilities</li> </ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
        </node>
    </header>
</headers>